[SPEAKER_00]: You mentioned that the sense of I am is real as such, in one of the past talks, but simply a mistaken identity.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I got that right.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when I try to find this real sense of I am, to properly identify it, I only find shifting feelings, thoughts and perceptions, leaving me confused about what exactly is real about my identity, if I can't locate it anywhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: I guess the answer to that is just on the same level.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is real about your eyes?
[SPEAKER_00]: What is real about your ears?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is real about your sense organs?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because none of them can experience itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, there is sight, there is sound, there is smell, there is tactile.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the expectation that real things are only the ones that I can make into sense objects, well, that's one of the deeply rooted wrong views.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because... what is that question even referring to then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, whoever asked that, obviously is referring to their own sense of self, that they have some recognition of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, they want it to be more.
[SPEAKER_01]: They want to make it more palpable.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the wrong views, expectations.
[SPEAKER_01]: I want to measure it.
[SPEAKER_01]: They want to examine it as a sense object.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fact is that they were looking for something, means there was some perception of the sense of self, sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because otherwise, like, the entire question and the words and terminology used would be completely unintelligible if you don't even know what it refers to.
[SPEAKER_01]: But they obviously have some sense of I am.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, what do they know what they're trying to find?
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Instead of being preoccupied in trying to find it, recognize the sense is already there, peripherally.
[SPEAKER_01]: As something that can never be directly examined, yet it always exists in the background.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just like the eye.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just like the eye, just like the ears.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because people get confused, because you can touch your eye and you think that's the eye that sees, but it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: The internal sense base, the eye that cannot see itself, is inaccessible to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter how much you touch it, how much you look at the picture of it, how much you stare in the mirror, what you're seeing is the sight, not the thing because of which the sight is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why when the Buddha described the internal senses, similarly it's like the empty villages.
[SPEAKER_01]: They get raided, defined by basically that which they're not.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's the same with the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Instead of following the natural expectation of finding it as a palpable, measurable thing, object of your senses, or of your thought, put that tendency aside, don't follow it, and instead ask yourself, well, what am I even trying to find?
[SPEAKER_01]: That vague sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I obviously have some recognition of its vagueness, otherwise I wouldn't, as I said, I wouldn't even set off searching for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're not just searching for an abstract idea that you don't understand what it refers to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you were, then why are you even looking for it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Say, if it's an abstract idea, you hear about sense of self, you have absolutely no idea what the sense of I am means.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have no reference.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it doesn't exist for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why would you be looking for it on the level of the sense objects?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why would you be questioning its realness, because it doesn't appear as much as...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you already kind of know that it's always there in the background.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's felt ambiguous, not as palpable.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you want it to be more so, because, again, that's what you deem as real, that's what you deem as necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's why you'll never get it that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like that, you know, the old simile I used to give, like, when you look at the stars at the night, and if you pick a bright star and stare at it, don't let your eyes look elsewhere, it's like thousands of peripheral little stars will appear.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you try to look at any of them, you just see blackness, because they can only be seen with peripheral vision.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you don't accept that, and you keep staring, you're just going to meet more and more frustration, because, again,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, one could come up with a view that, well, then, the sense of self doesn't exist, because I cannot directly find it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is it that doesn't exist, then, where they refer to, if it doesn't exist?
[SPEAKER_01]: If it truly doesn't exist, what are you referring to as non-existent?
[SPEAKER_00]: That thing that you are denying.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could more accurately say it doesn't exist as much.
[SPEAKER_01]: As much to the layers, to the levels, to the extents that I deem existence to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fact that I can think it,
[SPEAKER_01]: Peripherally, the fact that I can deny it, means that has to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Something has to be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So what can we say that something is?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, again, you fall back into the same question.
[SPEAKER_01]: What could I say that something is, means how could I make that something to be more than it is, because I don't like the ambiguity of it, and my mind is not used to seeing it as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need to make it more palpable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, any question, what is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it not?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it both?
[SPEAKER_01]: It revolves around, come on, make it more than it is, so that I can deal with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why Buddha wouldn't answer those questions, because he's just reinforcing the very kind of wrong view and the very wrong way of going about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that not quite as real sense of self is real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: To that extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, instead of trying to interfere or change or modify the extent, you need to learn how to see it impartially.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, that is a... you said that that is a sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: The owner is a product or a symptom of this assumption of ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, theoretically speaking, but practically that knowledge is irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just gonna serve as an excuse and explanation of what my sense of self is, which is, again, done for the sake of making it more definable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sense of self is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ownership is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cannot be accessed directly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always in the background.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always peripheral.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's a symptom of the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like...
[SPEAKER_01]: The heat is there because there is obviously fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the fire is there because the fuel is constantly provided for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So if you try to get rid of the heat...
[SPEAKER_01]: While still feeding the fire, well, it's a very futile endeavor.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's pretty much what people are doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: They...
[SPEAKER_01]: I try to deal with heat, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: with the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: I try to do this, I do that, it's anātā.
[SPEAKER_01]: Repeat anātā mantras, and deny it, and say it's not real, and science has explained that everything is constantly changing, da-da-da-da-da.
[SPEAKER_01]: While still inadvertently and ignorantly continuing to fuel the very fuel,
[SPEAKER_01]: The very fire because of which the heat, it's still going to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter how much you deny it as an afterthought, it's still going to be felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still going to burn.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, you recognize, yeah, this heat is a bit too hot.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's burning.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's too much.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do I get rid of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, by extinguishing the underlying fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is that underlying fire?
[SPEAKER_01]: Actions rooted in greed, aversion, distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignorance, resistance, hindrances, denial, unbeneficial, basically, acts by body, speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the fire.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the fuel for the fire.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's also why you have to train in it, to see it, and to get benefits from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because just providing an answer will not immediately extinguish the fire.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or even just, like, not providing the fuel for a day or two,
[SPEAKER_01]: will not immediately show you that the fire is lessening.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, because it was overloaded with fuel before that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is a bit of a delay that you have to, as I say, endure until you recognize that the fire is lessening and the heat is diminishing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or the fire is out and then the fire is out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Eventually, it will be out, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can have a view that the fire can go out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, magically, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why I say the sense of self is real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ambiguous, peripheral, not directly accessible, but it is real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the heat is real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not seeing the heat as an indirect by-product of an underlying problem,
[SPEAKER_01]: Will exactly make you go about it the way people go about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Try to make the sense of self into something measurable, something deniable, something that's not real, something that's an illusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, just denying the heat because you can't find the fire.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then just trying to cope by saying, well, you know, it's not real anyway and what is it anyway when I can't?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you touch the heat?
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you see the heat?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, it's there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: Burning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pressuring.
[SPEAKER_00]: The fueling is palpable.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can, you know...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, if you make the right associations.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not going to be seen on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not going to make the connection between seemingly random acts of desire, irritation and stuff, and then subsequent heat that pressures you in regard to completely different things.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why the learning is necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you start to look for the right connections and putting two and two together.
[SPEAKER_01]: And initially, yeah, you might even have to take it on faith that certain acts are increasing the heat, but you don't see the connection well.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have nothing to lose if you take it on faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the actions that are required from you to cultivate are beneficial even in the worldly sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't follow the desires blindly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't act out of anger by body, speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't entertain such thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, well, that's a good thing anyway, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody values that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even people have no interest in dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you ask them, is anger bad?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: How is anger felt?
[SPEAKER_01]: Pleasantly or unpleasantly?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: How is desire felt?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you can't get what you want, but desire remains there, highlighted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it would be good if you weren't there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be good if you would be in a bit more control in regard to those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it would be nice, it would be...
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be peaceful, wouldn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind would be quieter, the mind would be more content.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have nothing to lose, even if you take it in faith.
[SPEAKER_01]: That those kind of behaviors and not following those types of other unbeneficial behaviors is good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Plus, as the Buddha said in his instructions, it's... as a result of those things, the heat will lessen.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a result of those things, your own kind of need and compulsion for things to be clearly palpable, more defined, to be real, that will diminish as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: You recognize that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, look at that thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not as real.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, look at that thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not...
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't put my finger on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: The nature of being unable to put a finger on something is real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ambiguity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Uncertainty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't need to change it in order to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see it for what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you go over doubt as well, overcome the doubt, the uncertainty.
[SPEAKER_01]: You overcome the doubt by recognizing uncertainty real as such, and not feeling justified in automatically trying to get rid of it or explain in a way.